Lowell, Mass. Eliot Union Church records, 1830-1969.
Congregational Library & Archives
Lowell, Mass. Eliot Union Church records, 1830-1969.
RG0113
Congregational Library & Archives
5.94 Cubic Feet
(8 boxes)
The Appleton Congregational Church in Lowell, Massachusetts, was organized in 1830. In 1873, the church building was sold to the First Presbyterian Church and the church moved to a new building along Eliot Street to become the Eliot Street Church. The Kirk Street Church was organized in 1845. In 1919, the Eliot and Kirk Street Churches merged to form the Eliot Union Church. In 1955, the Eliot Union Church merged with the First Presbyterian Church to form the Eliot Presbyterian Church. The collection contains church administrative records, membership records, auxiliary group records, and scrapbooks.
Appleton Street Church (Lowell, Mass.)
Eliot Church (Lowell, Mass.)
Eliot Union Church (Lowell, Mass.)
First Presbyterian Church (Lowell, Mass.)
Kirk Street Church (Lowell, Mass.)
Conditions Governing Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Some Kirk Street Church materials were deposited at an undetermined date before 1981. The majority of the collection was donated to the Congregational Library & Archive by the Eliot Presbyterian Church in November, 1991; no accession number.
Historical Note
The Appleton Congregational Church in Lowell, Massachusetts, also known as the Second Congregational Church, was organized in 1830. The church's meeting house was located along Appleton Street. In 1873 the church building was sold to the First Presbyterian Church and a new church building was constructed at the corner of Eliot and Summer Streets. At this point, the church changed its name to Eliot Church.
The Kirk Street Church, also known as the Fourth Congregational Church, was organized in 1845. The church was initially poor with a fairly young membership. The church building was given to the town of Lowell to make way for a high school in 1916.
The Eliot Church and Kirk Street Church merged in 1919 to form the Eliot Union Church. This church continued to worship at the Eliot Street location. In 1955 the Eliot Union Church merged with the First Presbyterian Church to form the Eliot Presbyterian Church. The old Appleton Street Church was given to the Salvation Army after the merger of First Presbyterian and Eliot Union Church.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the records of the Eliot Union Church, in Lowell, Massachusetts, as well as the records of the two churches that merged to form the Eliot Union Church: the Eliot Church and the Kirk Street Church. The collection contains church administrative records, such as financial records and meeting minutes, membership records, including baptismal records and marriage records, auxiliary group records, and scrapbooks that document the weekly activities of the church.
Arrangement
This series has been arranged into the three series listed below. The Kirk Street Church records series has been further divided into three subseries. The collection has generally been arranged into chronological order. Some closely related materials, and materials which begin where a previous item ended, have been topically grouped together within the chronological order to assist discoverability.
Series 1: Eliot Church records, 1830-1918
Series 2: Kirk Street Church records, 1845-1919
Subseries 1: Administrative records, 1845-1919
Subseries 2: Membership and auxiliary group records, 1845-1919
Subseries 3: Scrapbooks, 1879-1917
Series 3: Eliot Union Church records, 1857-1969
Baptismal records.; Church finance.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Marriage records.; Pews and pew rights.; Scrapbooks.; Women -- Societies and clubs.; Worship programs.; Eliot Presbyterian Church (Lowell, Mass.); Lowell (Mass.) -- Church history.
- Eliot Church records, 1830 1918; 1830-1918
  Scope and Contents
  This subseries contains the records of the Eliot Church. These records include church records, membership records, records relating to a pastor's Bible class, an address authored by John M. Greene, records for the King's Daughters auxiliary group (continued in the Eliot Union Church records), and a leaflet that describes the value of the church's building.
  - Membership records, 1830 1919; 1830-1919 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Church records, 1830 1859; 1830-1859 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Membership records, 1853 1914; 1853-1914 (Box 3, Volume 2)
  - Church records, 1856 1875; 1856-1875 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Pastor's Bible class records, 1887 1907; 1887-1907 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - John M. Greene address, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - King's Daughters records, 1916 1918; 1916-1918 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Church value leaflet, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Kirk Street Church records, 1845 1919; 1845-1919
  This series contains the records of the Kirk Street Church. The records include administrative records, such as church records and financial records, membership records, including vital records, Sunday school records, auxiliary group records, and scrapbooks. The scrapbooks document weekly activities at the church.
  - Administrative records, 1845 1919; 1845-1919
    This subseries contains records related to the administration of the Kirk Street Church and contains both church records and financial records. The church records largely document the administrative history of the church and contain meeting minutes. The financial records document the finances of the church and also include records related to the church building and pews.
    - Church records, 1845 1888; 1845-1888 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    - Church records, 1888 1919; 1888-1919 (Box 2, Volume 2)
    - Financial records, 1845 1875; 1845-1875 (Box 2, Volume 6)
    - Financial records, 1876 1901; 1876-1901 (Box 2, Volume 7)
    - Financial records, 1901 1919; 1901-1919 (Box 2, Volume 8)
    - Subscriptions and collections, 1845 1881; 1845-1881 (Box 2, Volume 4)
    - Pew records, 1845 1887; 1845-1887 (Box 2, Volume 5)
    - Proprietors records, 1845 1916; 1845-1865, 1916 (Box 2, Volume 3)
    - Sermon notes, 1858 1861; 1858-1861 (Box 1, Volume 9)
    - Thirtieth anniversary sermon, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Manual, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Service programs, 1899 1919; 1899-1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cash book, 1904 1919; 1904-1919 (Box 2, Volume 9)
    - Letter to mayor, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Membership and auxiliary group records, 1845 1919; 1845-1919
    This subseries contains records related to the membership, and member activities, of the Kirk Street Church. This subseries also contains records related to the Kirk Street Sunday school and Christian Endeavour auxiliary group. The membership records contain marriage records, baptismal records, and records of admission and dismission. The Sunday school records contain information about students as well as records about the administration of the Sunday school. The Christian Endeavour records contain the meeting minutes for the group.
    - Membership and baptismal records, 1845 1874; 1845-1874 (Box 1, Volume 5)
    - Membership records, 1845 1911; 1845-1911 (Box 1, Volume 6)
    - Membership records, 1857 1914; 1857-1914 (Box 1, Volume 7)
    - Membership records, 1899 1919; 1899-1919 (Box 1, Volume 8)
    - Sunday school records, 1869 1871; 1869-1871 (Box 1, Volume 10)
    - Sunday school records, 1872 1873; 1872-1873 (Box 1, Volume 11)
    - Sunday school records, 1875 1914; 1875-1914 (Box 1, Volume 12)
    - Sunday school records, 1883 1890; 1883-1890 (Box 1, Volume 13)
    - Sunday school register, 1888 1889; 1888-1889 (Box 1, Volume 14)
    - Sunday school register, 1889 1890; 1889-1890 (Box 1, Volume 15)
    - Christian Endeavor records, 1883 1890; 1883-1890 (Box 1, Volume 16)
  - Scrapbooks, 1879 1917; 1879-1917
    This subseries contains scrapbooks created by the Kirk Street Church. These scrapbooks document the near weekly activities and happenings at the church. The scrapbooks primarily contain newspaper clippings and Sunday service programs. The scrapbooks also contain various ephemera created for various programs, events, and gatherings held at the church.
    - Scrapbook, 1879 1886; 1879-1886 (Box 6, Volume 1)
    - Scrapbook, 1888 1890; 1888-1890 (Box 6, Volume 3)
    - Scrapbook, 1890 1896; 1890-1896 (Box 6, Volume 5)
    - Scrapbook, 1896 1898; 1896-1898 (Box 8, Volume 2)
    - Scrapbook, 1898 1900; 1898-1900 (Box 8, Volume 1)
    - Scrapbook, 1900 1902; 1900-1902 (Box 8, Volume 3)
    - Scrapbook, 1903 1904; 1903-1904 (Box 7, Volume 3)
    - Scrapbook, 1904 1906; 1904-1906 (Box 5, Volume 2)
    - Scrapbook, 1907 (Box 6, Volume 2)
    - Scrapbook, 1908 1909; 1908-1909 (Box 6, Volume 4)
    - Scrapbook, 1910 (Box 5, Volume 3)
    - Scrapbook, 1911 (Box 5, Volume 4)
    - Scrapbook, 1912 1913; 1912-1913 (Box 7, Volume 4)
    - Scrapbook, 1914 1915; 1914-1915 (Box 7, Volume 5)
    - Scrapbook, 1915 1917; 1915-1917 (Box 7, Volume 6)
- Eliot Union Church records, 1857 1969; 1857-1969
  This series contains the records of the Eliot Union Church. The records largely start in 1919, when the Eliot and Kirk Street churches merged, but a few record books begin prior to the merger. The membership records, in particular, appear to contain copies of earlier records. This series contains church and administrative records, membership records, auxiliary group records, as well as miscellaneous ephemera.
  - Membership records, 1857 1952; 1857-1952 (Box 4, Volume 1)
  - First Presbyterian Church materials, 1897 1969; 1897-1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    This folder contains ephemera related to the First Presbyterian Church in Lowell. The First Presbyterian Church and Eliot Union Church merged in 1956. The folder contains two photographs in glass of the church's exterior, a 1933 service of dedication program, a seventy-fifth anniversary program, a one hundredth anniversary program, an in memoriam for Rev. Robert Court, and an explainer, with photographs, for the "Historic Windows" of the church.
  - King's Daughters programs, 1911 1937; 1911-1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - King's Daughters records, 1918 1920; 1918-1920 (Box 4, Volume 2)
  - King's Daughters records, 1920 1922; 1920-1922 (Box 4, Volume 3)
  - King's Daughters records, 1922 1925; 1922-1925 (Box 5, Volume 1)
  - King's Daughters records, 1930 1940; 1930-1940 (Box 4, Volume 4)
  - Church records, 1919 1953; 1919-1953 (Box 7, Volume 1)
    Separated Materials
    The "Miscellaneous church records, 1931-1954" were removed from this volume for preservation purposes. The item was removed from the back of the book.
  - Girls Service Club records, 1919 1928; 1919-1928 (Box 4, Volume 5)
  - Girls Service Club records, 1928 1929; 1928-1929 (Box 4, Volume 6)
  - Church committee records, 1921 1928; 1921-1928 (Box 7, Volume 2)
    The "Poems, undated" were removed from this volume for preservation purposes. The item was removed from page 55.
  - Miscellaneous church records, 1931 1954; 1931-1954 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Materials in this folder were removed from the "Church records, 1919-1953" for preservation purposes. This item was found in the very back of that record book.
  - Joachim M. Reis testimonial, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - John W. MacNeil resignation clipping, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Eliot Service League records, 1950 1955; 1950-1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Historical sketch and window history, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Poems, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Materials in this folder were removed from the "Committee records, 1921-1928" for preservation purposes. This item was found on page 55 of that record book.